Guide to the Franklin Humanities Institute Records, 1999-2019 UA.26.03.0030
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Franklin Humanities Institute Records
1999-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Hope Franklin Humanities Institute
UA.26.03.0030
0.75 Linear Feet
108 Gigabytes
The John Hope Franklin Humanities Institute at Duke University, often referred to as the Franklin Humanities Institute (FHI), is an interdisciplinary humanities center. The Franklin Humanities Institute Records include annual reports, meeting notes, position descriptions, and planning documents. Also includes photographs and video recordings of the event "From Slavery to Freedom Lab: Black Women Writers at Work."
Access Restrictions
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Provenance
The Franklin Humanities Institute Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 2017 and 2019.
Biographical / Historical
The John Hope Franklin Humanities Institute at Duke University, often referred to as the Franklin Humanities Institute (FHI), is an interdisciplinary humanities center. The FHI's mission is "to encourage and enable serious humanistic inquiry, and to promote a heightened awareness of the centrality of the huamnities to the quality of human life, social interaction, and scholarship in all fields" and it emphasizes "scholarly work that examines issues of social equity, especially research on race and ethnicity."
The FHI was founded in 1999 by Vice Provost for Interdisciplinary Studies Cathy Davidson and Dean of the Humanities and Social Sciences Karla Holloway, and was named for John Hope Franklin, James B. Duke Professor of History. FHI provides a variety of programs and initiatives, including the Humanities Laboratory initiative, which provides groups of faculty, graduate students, and undergraduate students with spaces for collaborative work; a Faculty Book Manuscript Workshop; an annual residential seminar of faculty, graduate students, and professional staff; and annual lectures, among others.
Sources: Franklin Humanities Institute about page, http://www.fhi.duke.edu/about.html, viewed 2017 July 06. Franklin Humanities Institute Wikipedia page, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franklin_Humanities_Institute, viewed 2017 July 06.
Related Materials
Cathy N. Davidson Papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
HASTAC Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Collection Overview
The Franklin Humanities Institute Records include materials from the FHI's first two decades, particularly annual reports, bylaws, meeting notes, position descriptions, grant application materials, and planning documents. Also includes photographs and video recordings of the event "From Slavery to Freedom Lab: Black Women Writers at Work."
Interdisciplinary approach in education; Indisciplinary research; African American women scholars; Machine-readable artifacts; John Hope Franklin Humanities Institute; Davidson, Cathy N., 1949-
- FHI Report Meetings, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until 2031
- FHI Job Descriptions, 2005 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2030
- FHI Library Fellow, 2006-2007 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2032
- FHI Co-Conveners and Participants, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
- FHI: Cheri Ross, undated (Box 1)
- Seminar Fellows, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
- FHI Bylaws, circa 2002 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2027
- FHI Budget Overage, 2004-2005 (Box 1)
- FHI Seminar Co-Convened by Wald and Lenoir, 2006-2007 (Box 1)
- FHI Innovative Humanities Course, 2005 (Box 1)
- FHI Meetings with Cheri and Srinivas, 2004-2005 (Box 1)
- Farred Phone Charges, 2005 (Box 1)
- FHI Director Search, 2006 (Box 1)
- Scholars at Risk, 2004 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2029
- FHI Review, 2005 Fall (Box 1)
- FHI Co-Conveners, 2006-2007 (Box 1)
- Mellon Foundation Franklin Humanities Institute, 2007-2008 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2033
- FHI Replacement Teaching, 2004-2005 (Box 1)
- FHI Review, 2004 (Box 1)
- FHI Seminar Participants, 2004-2005 (Box 1)
- Budget, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
- Replacement Teaching/Graduate Fellowships, 2003 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2028
- Co-Conveners, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
- Co-Conveners, 2004-2005 (Box 1)
- Deb Willis Exhibition, 2004 January (Box 1)
- JHFI Associate Director Position Description, 2001 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2026
- Co-Conveners, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
- Seminars, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
- Meetings, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
- Mellon Grant, 2002-2005 (Box 1)
- RFP, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
- FHI Support Services, undated (Box 1)
- FHI Projects, 2007 (Box 1)
- Srinivas Aravamudan, 2005 (Box 1)
- Annual Report, 2003 August (Box 1)
- Reparations, 2003 (Box 1)
- FHI Review, 2003 (Box 1)
- Weekly Meetings, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
- Franklin Institute Advisory Board, 1999-2003 (Box 1)
- FI Director, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
- Goals, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
- Higginbotham, Evelyn B., 2002 (Box 1)
- Seminar Fellows, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
- Replacement Teacher Letters, 2002 (Box 1)
- Darity, Sandy, 2003 (Box 1)
- Budget, 2006-2007 (Box 1)
- From Slavery to Freedom Lab: Black Women Writers at Work photographs and flyers, 2019; 281 files; 3.11 GB. (Digital-materials UA26030030-SET-0001)
  Scope and Contents
  Publicity flyers and photographs of participants. Files are in JPG, PNG, and PDF formats.
  Access note. Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
- From Slavery to Freedom Lab: Black Women Writers at Work video recordings, 2019; 4 files; 105 GB (Digital-materials UA26030030-SET-0002, Digital-materials UA26030030-SET-0003)
  Video recordings of panels and talks. Includes recordings of the 1st and 2nd panels, as well as small recordings of introductory remarks. Speakers include Duke Provost Sally Kornbluth, Dr. Lamonte Aidoo, Dr. Jasmine Nicole Cobb, Dr. Farah Jasmine Griffin, Dr. Beverly Guy-Sheftall, Dr. Deborah McDowell, Dr. Cheryl Wall, Dr. Michele Wallace, Dr. Carole Boyce Davies, Dr. Hazel Carby, Dr. Thadious Davis, and Dr. Mary Helen Washington. Files are in MOV format.
  Access Note. Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
- Budget reports, 2017-2018; 4 files; 4.2 MB (Digital-materials UA26030030-SET-0001)
  Includes drafts and instructions for Report to the Universities Priorities Committee. Files in PDF format.
  Restricted until 2043
- External Review reports, 2017-2018; 3 files; 37 MB (Digital-materials UA26030030-SET-0001)
  Includes External Review Committee Report; External Review Self-Study; and Franklin Humanities Institute Response to the External Review. Files in PDF format.
- Grant proposals and reports, 2005-2019; 6 files; 11 MB (Digital-materials UA26030030-SET-0001)
  Includes Mellon grant proposals and reports. Files in PDF and DOC formats.
  Restricted until 2044
- Policies and Procedures, 2016-2019; 3 files; 3 MB (Digital-materials UA26030030-SET-0001)
  Includes bylaws and faculty appointment and promotion guidelines.
- Reports, 2012-2019; 9 files; 45 MB (Digital-materials UA26030030-SET-0001)
  Includes annual reports and faculty directory. Files in PDF and XLSX formats.
- Strategic Planning, 2006; 2009; 2 files; 3 MB (Digital-materials UA26030030-SET-0001)
  Includes 2006 Strategic Plan and 2009 Strategic Statement. Files in PDF format.
  Restricted until 2034